בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, today's דף daf *daf* is קכ"א Kuf Kaf
Aleph, *Kuf-Kaf-Aleph*, 121, and we pick up with תנן התם *Tnan Hatam*,
middle of the דף daf. *daf*, line starts with the word מומחה
*Mumche*, and then there's a little ג' *Gimmel* in a half parentheses,
so really ממש *mamash* in the smack middle of the דף *daf*
there. תנן התם *Tnan Hatam*, so we're talking again about the whole
issue about בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzelofchad. *Bnot Tzelafchad* and whether the land
was... we just got through saying that that generation, they were allowed
to marry whomever they wanted. Future generations could marry whomever they wanted,
and the restriction to only marry within the family or within the
tribe was limited to the people of that generation who were in
a similar circumstance as בנות צלפחד Tzelofchad *Bnot Tzelafchad*, but not to
the בנות צלפחד Tzelofchad *Bnot Tzelafchad* themselves who were advised not to,
but not prohibited from doing it. And so they followed the advice.
All right, so with that background we're going to quote a famous
משנה Mishnah *Mishna* in תענית Taanit *Taanit* because it's going to have
some intersection with what we're discussing. תנן התם *Tnan Hatam*, we taught
over there in תענית Taanit *Taanit*. אמר רבי שמעון בן גמליאל, לא
היו ימים טובים לישראל כחמישה עשר באב וכיום הכיפורים *Amar Rabbi Shimon
ben Gamliel, lo hayu yamim tovim leYisrael kechamisha asar beAv ukYom HaKippurim*.
There were never as many, the greatest joyous days for Israel as
the 15th of אב Av? *Av* and יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom
Kippur*, what was so now, שבהן בנות ישראל Yisrael, יוצאות בכלי לבן
שאולין שלא לבייש את מי שאין לו *shebehen benot Yisrael yotzot bechelei
lavan she'ulin shelo levayesh et mi she'ein lo*. Everybody would go out,
all the young women would go out, they would borrow clothes from
their
friends so that somebody who needed to borrow clothes wouldn't be embarrassed
that they needed to borrow. So everybody borrowed, even people that had
their own clothes. So you could borrow from
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like the princesses would borrow from the
daughter of the כהן kohen גדול *Cohen Gadol*, so you'd probably borrow
clothes from a friend who would have the same quality or taste
as you did, and maybe you would exchange your clothes, but nevertheless
there was this whole thing of everybody borrowing, borrowing. So if you
really needed to borrow, you wouldn't be embarrassed that you'd have to
borrow. And then they would all go out and everybody knows they
would dance and they would sort of say, you know, it would
be a young man, lift up your eyes, pick the woman who's
appropriate for you. So it was this joyous day of courtship and
so on. So I just have to tell the story that I
always tell when we do this משנה *Mishna*. Michael, don't ruin it,
you ruined it last time. So anyway, so the משנה *Mishna* says
that it says what did the beautiful girls, or the ברייתא Braitisa:
*Braita* I think says, it says what did the beautiful young women
say? They said, young man, look at beauty because a woman is
only for her looks. And what did the ones from good family
say? It said יחוס *Yichus*, it said young man, look toward יחוס
*Yichus* because a woman is for her children. So the בריסקר רב
*Brisker Rav* said, okay, but what did the ones... and then it
says, and the ones who were neither
beautiful nor from a good family, they said young man, pick a
wife לשם שמיים *LeShem Shamayim*.
So the בריסקר רב *Brisker Rav* says, okay, that's what the beautiful
ones said and the מיוחסות *meyuchasot* ones said and the ones that
were neither. How about the ones that were both beautiful and מיוחסות
*meyuchasot*? What did they say? He said they were already married.
So anyway. All right, so the משנה *Mishna*... so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, so what was so special about these days? So it
says בשלמא יום הכיפורים *bishlama Yom HaKippurim*, so I understand what was
so joyous about יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, יום סליחה ומחילה
*yom slicha umechila*. It was a day of forgiveness, right? That was
the day that, I mean in general it's a day of forgiveness
and historically לוחות אחרונות *luchot acharonot*. It was the day that משה
Moshe *Moshe* came down with their second set of לוחות *Luchot* because
you do the whole math like so if he got the לוחות
*Luchot* on what do you call it, on שבועות *Shavuot*, so coming
up, which סיון *Sivan*, לוחות *Luchot* on שבועות *Shavuot*, right, מתן
תורה Torah.
*Matan Torah* was on שבועות *Shavuot*, which is like ו' סיון *Vav
Sivan*. So then 40 days later is י"ז בתמוז *Shiv'ah Asar B'Tammuz*.
He comes down on י"ז בתמוז *Shiv'ah Asar B'Tammuz*, he breaks it.
He goes back up.
Now if you read the story in שמות *Shemot* or the story
in דברים *Devarim*, it sounds like there was only one 40-day period
that followed, but חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* sort of bring the two stories
together and they say there were two 40-day periods that followed. So
if you combine the two 40-day periods, right, so from י"ז בתמוז
*Shiv'ah Asar B'Tammuz* plus 40 days gets you I think like the
28th of אלול *Elul*, of אב Av. *Av*, and then 17th of
תמוז *Tammuz* plus 40 days gets you the 28th of אב Av
*Av*, and then plus 40 days gets you to יום כיפור Yom
Kippur. *Yom Kippur*. Okay, if you sort of see, you can roughly
do that math in your head. So anyway, that's יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*. That's also could be why יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* is designated
as יום סליחה ומחילה *yom slicha umechila*, day of forgiveness, because then
they re-got the לוחות *Luchot*, so they were like starting all over
again. Now what does it have to do with a day of
courtship is not clear,
but to the degree that you understand that like the whole idea
of the metaphor in the נביאים *Nevi'im* of God and בני ישראל
Bnei Yisrael *Bnei Yisrael* like the husband-wife type of a metaphor, and
חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* sort of also use this with the breaking of
the לוחות *Luchot*, that was like a tearing up of
a... so then, you know, when they sort of, you know, then
they got, then they got the לוחות again, it was like a,
you know, a getting back together. So, so that at least, I
don't know, the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that, but you know, you
want to understand that it's not just a day of joy, but
why was it connected to this whole day of courtship?
Anyway, so yeah, it’s a very different atmosphere. Exactly. That's
right.
Yeah, one wonders how much time they spent in שול Shul if
they were doing this on יום כיפור.
Anyway, so let me just tell you this, the גמרא Gemara.
in תענית also just mentions that
on יום כיפור it's getting back to, oh, that's nice, the sort
of re, yeah, yeah, the, yeah, that's a very nice point, the
husband-wife getting back together. So,
okay.
And also, you know, the degree here that the women were the
ones that were initiating, you know, so here the whole sort of
rejoining of בני ישראל B'nei Yisrael. and God came through משה's Moshe.
prayers, you know, and sort of getting God to agree to come
back. So you could sort of see some type of a parallel
there. Anyway, so we get יום כיפור. So אב בחמישה עשר מאי
היא? Av b'Chamisha Asar mai hi? What's the significance about the 15th
of אב? Av. Why was that such a joyous day? So אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, יום שהותרו שבטים
לבוא זה בזה. yom she'hutru shevatim lavo zeh ba'zeh. So this is
why we're bringing it in here, because one answer is, that was
the day that the tribes were allowed, they didn't have this restriction
that applied to the women who inherited, you know, a portion in
the land through their father, whatever, that we said that restriction applied
to that generation, that they could not marry men from another tribe.
So therefore, when that generation had ended, now that does not,
you know, it doesn't say exactly when. Fifty years maybe after they
entered ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, when all the members of that generation
died out, then the restrictions no longer applied. Okay, so therefore, that
was a day in which, you know, everybody was free to marry
whomever they wished. So that really works very nicely, right, with the
whole idea of the women going out and saying, you know, pick
whom you will. It's all about, you know, getting married and being
free to marry who you see as most appropriate. הטוב בעיניהם תהיינה
לנשים, Hatov b'eineihem tihyena l'nashim, right? And the משנה there says, בחור
שא נא עיניך, bachur sa na einecha, you know, lift up your
eyes, right? So anyway, and also you've got women sort of being
more the initiators, which ties in of course to the whole story
of בנות צלפחד. So there's no פסוק pasuk or anything that identifies
that as the day, but it's a nice way of connecting those
two events. Okay, so that's what he says. יום שהותרו שבטים לבוא
זה בזה. Yom she'hutru shevatim lavo zeh ba'zeh. מאי דרש? Mai darash?
Where did he, what, where does he make this דרשה? drasha? From
what we said yesterday, זה הדבר, Zeh hadavar, this is the matter.
דבר זה לא יהיה נוהג אלא בדור הזה. Davar zeh lo yehe
noheg ela b'dor hazeh. It was limited to that generation. So he
has a tradition or, you know, or that that ended, that generation
had fully died out and the restriction went away on the 15th
of אב. Av. רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Rabbah bar
bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, יום שהותרו שבט בנימין לבוא בקהל. yom
she'hutru shevet Binyamin lavo b'kahal. Another nice tie into issues of courtship
and marriage. After the whole story of פילגש בגבעה, Pilegesh b'Givah, right,
they did not want to let, you know, בנימין Binyamin marry into
any of the other tribes. But on that day they were able
to remarry in. Now how did that happen? דכתיב, De'chtiv, because the
verse says,
ואיש ישראל נשבע במצפה לאמר, V'ish Yisrael nishba b'Mitzpah l'emor, they took
an oath in מצפה Mitzpah saying, איש ממנו לא יתן בתו לבנימין
לאשה, Ish mimenu lo yiten bito l'Binyamin l'isha, no man from among
us will give his daughter to בנימין Binyamin for a wife. Right,
that's also why the sort of tribe of בנימין Binyamin sort of
like snatched these women because they weren't being given willingly. מאי דרש?
Mai darash? So what's the דרשה drasha that says that that had
a sort of an expiration date? ממנו ולא מבנינו. Mimenu v'lo mibaneinu.
Okay, we won't give our daughters, but our sons will give their
daughters. So in the next generation that restriction no longer applied. בנימין
Binyamin managed to get through that generation as the story they tell,
like I said, they snatched some women or whatever it was. Okay,
and then the next generation already that restriction had gone away. So
it's a very similar idea, right? There was restrictions about marriage, and
then everybody was free to marry whom they saw
fit, and so once again you have this as a day of
joy and of courtship. רב דימי בר יוסף אמר רב
נחמן,
Rav Dimi bar Yosef amar
Rav
Nachman, sorry, trying to bring in the דרשה drasha so it's already
a tangent to the tangent. Yeah, we, the reason we brought this
in was for the first answer. Now that we're discussing it we're
giving all the other answers. Okay, רב דימי בר יוסף אמר רב
נחמן, Rav Dimi bar Yosef amar Rav Nachman, יום שכלו בו מתי
מדבר. yom she'kalu vo metei midbar.
The day that all those who were dying out from the, of
that generation of the wilderness, so that's the, died out before they
entered into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Now why is that a joyous
thing? Well I guess the dying stopped and you were ready to
start fresh with a new generation. דאמר מר, D'amar mar, because the
master said, עד שלא כלו מתי מדבר, ad she'lo kalu metei midbar,
until those who died from the, you know, from the wilderness had
died out, לא היה דיבור עם משה. lo haya dibur im Moshe.
God did not speak directly to משה. Moshe. שנאמר, Shene'emar, ויהי כאשר
תמו כל אנשי המלחמה למות מקרב העם, vayi ka'asher tamu kol anshei
hamilchama lamut mikerev ha'am, and it was when all the people of
the, you know, of the army, meaning because they were counted like
יוצאי צבא, yotzei tzava, so the word צבא tzava was associated with
it and so on. Anyway, when the people of the... As soon
as that previous generation had fully died out, וסמוך ליה U'samuch lei
and the immediately next verses וידבר השם אלי לאמר Vay'dabber Hashem elai
lemor
God spoke to me. So that's a very bizarre juxtaposition. As soon
as they die out, God spoke to me. So it suggests that
somehow because they were still alive, God was not speaking to Moshe.
אלי היה הדיבור, Elai hayah hadibbur, God spoke to me. Now of
course the problem with this is that of course you read the
Torah and God is speaking to Moshe a lot during that period.
So a lot of the time it says ויאמר השם אל משה,
Vayomer Hashem el Moshe, not וידבר השם. Vay'dabber Hashem. And here there's
an emphasis of like וידבר, Vay'dabber, which has that sense of that
more immediate and intimate direct personal connection. But nevertheless, there are times
it says וידבר Vay'dabber during that 38 years anyway. So the רשב"ם
Rashbam tries to say, well maybe it means indirectly or maybe it
means until that point God spoke to Moshe only when necessary, but
from that point on God spoke to Moshe just because the relationship
was restored. But part of the message there is it's a powerful
message because we're always emphasizing פה אל פה אדבר בו, Peh el
peh adabber bo, Moshe was so great, he had this intimacy. And
of course the story, if you think about the story of the
מרגלים, Meraglim, like God says I'm going to wipe them all out
and I'll make you into a great nation, so we always think
it's like this unique relationship God has with Moshe. And the message
that חז"ל are communicating here is that God only spoke to Moshe
because of by virtue of בני ישראל. B'nei Yisrael So once בני
ישראל B'nei Yisrael. were in this state of divine displeasure, a phrase
used in the גמרא Gemara in תענית is they were like מנודה
לשמים, Menudeh lashamayim, they were like under the ban, God was, so
they were distanced from God, so Moshe was distanced from God as
well.
So there's something very powerful about that I think as I said
juxtaposing to the idea that in the aftermath of the מרגלים Meraglim
God says yeah who needs them, it'll just be me and you,
אעשה אותך לגוי גדול. E'eseh otcha l'goy gadol. And here saying actually
Moshe's relationship to God was due to the merit of בני ישראל.
Bnei Yisrael So it wasn't until they were like at that next
generation that that relationship was really like fully restored.
Now what does that have to do with it being a day
of courtship? I don't exactly get. I think that we don't see
a direct connection. Again you could once again speak about intimacy, פה
אל פה Peh el peh and so on, but again I think
that the relationship here to courtship is less than it was in
the previous answers. The other question is about the
aspect, until now the date of the 15th of אב Av, there
was no particular פסוק Pasuk to link it to. We just sort
of said that was their tradition that this happened on the 15th
of אב. Av? But here the רשב"ם Rashbam quotes a famous מדרש.
Midrash. And the מדרש Midrash says as follows: because once you're tying
it into the
דור המדבר, Dor Hamidbar, the חטא המרגלים Cheit Hamerraglim is identified as
being on תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. So תשעה באב Tisha B'Av is
pretty close to the 15th of אב. Av. So the רשב"ם Rashbam
quotes a מדרש Midrash that connects the two and says every year
on the 15th on the 9th of אב, Av, the anniversary of
the חטא המרגלים, Cheit Hamerraglim, everybody from that generation would dig a
grave,
this is like so creepy, this idea, would dig a grave and
go to lie down in the graves that they dug. And then
the next morning one 40th of them would have died and they
would have then been buried in the graves that they had dug
for
themselves and the remainder would get up. And each year another about
15,000 because 40 times 15,000 is 600,000. It's actually a little bit
more because there
were 38 years
anyway, so about 15,000-16,000 would remain in their graves each year. Now
what does that have to do with the 15th of אב? Av,
Then you would say they would all have died out by the
9th of אב. Av,
So according to this מדרש, Midrash, what happened was the way the
רשב"ם Rashbam reads it (תוספות Tosafot does not like this read for
a whole range of
reasons).
Where's this רשב"ם? Rashbam? It's right here at the end of this
גמרא. Gemara. You can read it inside if you want. Let me
just sort of finish explaining it. So according to this, God had
רחמנות Rachmanut with the last
generation and with the last group. So 15,000 actually of those from
the דור המדבר Dor Hamidbar actually did not die out and entered
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So what happened was they went into their
graves on the 9th of אב, Av. the last year on the
9th of אב, Av and then the next morning they got up.
And what's going on here? Nobody died. So they said let's try
again tomorrow night
because maybe we got the date wrong, maybe it wasn't the 9th
of אב, Av. maybe it was the 8th of אב. And they
kept on trying again and again until it was the 15th of
אב and they saw a full moon. So they realized, oh God
must have like forgiven us or whatever. So that was why it
was such this day of joy. That was the way the רשב"ם
Rashbam reads why it's connected to the 15th of אב. The irony
is then it's not the day that the מתי מדבר Metei midbar
totally died out. It's actually a different day, it's a day that
15,000 of the מתי מדבר Metei midbar had their decree waived. And
anyway it goes so much against the פסוקים, Psukim, the פסוקים Psukim
are לא נותר מהם איש כי אם כלב בן יפונה, Lo notar
mehem ish ki im Kaleiv ben Yefunneh, right, nobody remained. According to
this you had a major segment of people that remained. So תוספות
Tosafot does not like this מדרש Midrash at all, or certainly not
the way the רשב"ם Rashbam reads it. If you want to take
a look at it, it's at the bottom of קכ"א, שכלו בו
מתי מדבר. she'kalu bo Meisei Midbar.
He says the following: במדרש במדרש איכה, BaMidrash BaMidrash Eichah,
it's like one, two, three, like eight lines from the bottom or
ten lines from the bottom. במדרש איכה, BaMidrash Eichah, יום שביטלו בו
החפירה, yom she'bitlu bo hachafirah, the
חפירה, chafirah, the diggings. דאמר
רבי לוי,
De'amar
Rabbi
Levi, כל ערב תשעה באב kol erev Tisha B'Av היה כרוז יוצא,
הכול
יצאו לחפור חפירים, haya kruz yotzei, Hakol yetzu lachpor chafirim, וישנים בהם.
veyashenim bahem. ובשחרית הכרוז יוצא, ייבדלו החיים מן המתים. Uvshacharis hakruz yotzei,
yibadlu hachayim min hametim. Okay, everybody get up, the ones that are
alive get out of the graves, the ones that are dead stay
in your graves, okay? So we have this phrase like ייבדל לחיים,
yibadel lachayim, right, when you say somebody,
פלוני זכרונו לברכה Ploni zichrono livracha and so-and-so ייבדל לחיים. yibadel lachayim.
So anyway, ייבדלו חיים מן
המתים.
yibadlu chayim min
hametim.
Do you know where they get it from?
I don't know. But והיו בודקים אותם, ve'hayu bodkim otam, ונמצאו ט"ו
אלף ופרוטות, venimtzu tet-vav elef u'perutos, fifteen thousand and
change, חיסרון בכל שנה. chisaron bechol shana. וכך עשו מ"ם שנה. Vekach
asu mem shana. בשנה אחרונה Beshana achrona עשו כן. asu chen. בדקו
עצמן ונמצאו שלמים. Badku atzman venimtzu shlemim. אמרו, שמא טעינו בחשבון. Amru,
shema tainu bacheshbon. וכן ביו"ד וכן בי"א וכן בי"ב וכן בי"ג וכן
בי"ד, Vechen beyod vechen beyud-aleph vechen beyud-bet vechen beyud-gimmel vechen beyud-daled, עד
שנתמלא סיהרא ad shenismalei saihara until the moon was full. כיוון שנתמלא
סיהרא Keivan shenismalei saihara אמרו, ביטל הקדוש ברוך הוא אותה
גזרה קשה מעלינו. amru, bitel HaKadosh Baruch Hu osah gezeira kasha me'aleinu.
ועשו משתה ושמחה ויום טוב. Va'asu mishte v'simcha v'yom tov. Okay, so
that's the... תוספות, Tosfos, there's a long תוספות Tosfos here. He says,
for many reasons, he says first of all the פסוקים psukim are
very clear they all died out, and then it's not the day
that כלו בו מתי מדבר, kalu bo Meisei Midbar, it's the day
that they realized that they weren't all dying out. It doesn't really
fit what the גמרא Gemara is saying. You can take a look,
תוספות Tosfos is not at all...
No, he has a different way of reading it, but he basically
doesn't like it. He basically just says no, it's the day that
everybody finished dying out, end of story. Okay, so now back to
the גמרא. Gemara, The גמרא Gemara. says like this. עולא אמר, Ulla
amar,
יום שביטל בו הושע בן אלה פרדסאות yom she'bitel bo Hoshea ben
Elah pardesa'os שהושיב ירבעם על הדרכים, she'hoshib Yeravam al hadrachim, so שלא
יעלו ישראל לרגל. shelo ya'alu Yisrael leregel. So ירבעם בן נבט, Yeravam
ben Nevat, right, when they split off the
two kingdoms and he had these gold calves that were in דן
Dan as to be the center of worship, he was still afraid
that everybody from the northern kingdom, from ישראל, Yisrael, would go to
ירושלים Yerushalayim for the רגל. regel. And it's not good if you
want to have your own kingdom to have everybody recognize the spiritual
center being
elsewhere,
right? So what he did was he put guards on the highways
to make sure that when it was the time of the רגל,
regel, nobody could go to ירושלים Yerushalayim from the northern kingdom. Okay,
and הושע בן אלה, Hoshea ben Elah, he was one of the
northern kings, but
it says he wasn't good but he wasn't as bad as the
kings that preceded him. So in what way was he not as
bad as the kings that preceded him? So according to the גמרא,
Gemara it means that he allowed people, like he removed these guards.
Now why did he remove the guards? So the reason according to
the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains, if you look at the רשב"ם,
Rashbam, the last of the wide lines here at the top, four
or five lines from the top, יום שביטל הושע בן אלה פרדסאות
yom she'bitel Hoshea ben Elah pardesa'os שומרים, shomrim, כדתניא בסדר עולם, kedetanya
beSeder Olam, כשראה הושע בן אלה שגלו עגלי הזהב, kesheraa Hoshea ben
Elah shegalu eglei hazahav, because the golden calves that were their center
of worship in the northern kingdom had been taken by the enemy,
had been taken away. Of course, if anything, that's more of a
reason to stop people from going to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, but anyway,
עמד והעביר פרדסאות שהושיב ירבעם בן נבט amad ve'he'evir pardesa'os she'hoshib Yeravam
ben Nevat שלא יעלו ישראל לרגל. shelo ya'alu Yisrael leregel. שבכל מלכי
ישראל הוא אומר Shebechol malchei Yisrael hu omer וילך בדרך ירבעם בן
נבט vayelech bederech Yeravam ben Nevat ובחטאתו אשר החטיא את ישראל. uvachata'aso
asher hichti es Yisrael. All other kings it says they followed the
path of ירבעם. Yeravam.
אבל בהושע כתיב, Aval beHoshea ksiv, רק לא כמלכי ישראל אשר היו
לפניו. rak lo kemalchei Yisrael asher hayu lefanav. So there was something
that distinguished him, that he was not as bad as the previous
kings. So this understands that he did this and therefore somehow we're
identifying that as ט"ו באב. Tu B'Av. What does that have to
do with a day of courtship? Again, I don't know, unless once
again you talk about bringing, allowing the two
kingdoms to draw closer to one another, not keeping them separate from
one another. But again, these later answers don't fit in as well
with the themes of the courtship.
I know,
but isn't that all the more reason not to get the people
to go down and to recognize a different center of worship? Anyway,
alright, so now it says like this. רב מתנא אמר, Rav Masna
amar, another answer, יום שניתנו הרוגי ביתר לקבורה, yom shenisnu harugei Beitar
likvura, the day that those that were killed in ביתר Beitar in
the aftermath of the second בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, right, that they
had been all slaughtered and they were finally allowed to go ahead
and bury them. דאמר רב מתנא, De'amar Rav Masna, אותו יום שניתנו
הרוגי ביתר לקבורה, oso yom shenisnu harugei Beitar likvura, the day that
they were allowed to be buried, תקנו ביבנה הטוב והמטיב. tiknu b'Yavne
HaTov VeHaMeitiv. They established the fourth ברכה bracha of ברכת המזון, Birkas
HaMazon, which is considered like the add-on ברכה. bracha. You know, because
anyway the first three ברכות, brachos, the second and the third don't
begin
with
You don't normally say
אמן *Amen* after your own ברכה *bracha* anyway, but that sort of
identifies the first three as one unit and then the next one
starts at its own unit with a ברוך אתה *Baruch Ata*. So
that was a later ברכה *bracha* that was established in ברכת המזון
*Birkas Hamazon*. So what's הטוב והמטיב *Hatov Vehameitiv*? It's always this funny
I never really fully got the identification, I mean I understand why
you want to make a ברכה *bracha* for this, but its association
to the idea of eating food and so on, you know, but
food spoil I guess?
But maybe it's connected to בונה ירושלים Yerushalayim *Boneh Yerushalayim*. What does
ירושלים *Yerushalayim* have to do with, you know, with the eating food,
you know? So I mean, it's interesting, I'll just say one minute,
you know, the first ברכה *bracha* is הזן את הכל *Hazan es
Hakol*, right, which is just about food, which is sort of universal.
על הארץ ועל המזון *Al Ha'aretz Ve'al Hamazon* really more reflects the
פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in the תורה Torah. *Torah*. וברכת את ה' אלוהיך
על הארץ הטובה אשר Asher נתן לך *Uveirachta es Hashem Elokecha al
ha'aretz hatovah asher nasan lach*. Right, the תורה Torah, *Torah* imagines that
you're not just thanking God for food, the תורה Torah *Torah* points
it in the context of you're living in Israel, you're growing fruit
in Israel, you're harvesting your fruit, your produce, you're eating your produce,
and therefore it's sort of like the whole idea of bringing ביכורים
*Bikkurim*. You know, you're grateful to God for giving you the land,
right, where it's all in the context about getting the land. So
it has a much more broader significance, not just God puts food
on my table but has allowed me to be like live in
my own country, give me this land and so on. So that's
like על הארץ ועל המזון *Al Ha'aretz Ve'al Hamazon*. So presumably, you
know, בונה ירושלים *Boneh Yerushalayim*, once we've introduced the theme of ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael*, presumably that's where ירושלים *Yerushalayim* comes in.
Although again it is a pretty strange theme in ברכת המזון *Birkas
Hamazon*. But you know, maybe you understand that like okay well if
the whole point is to recognize that we are living in the
land and in our country and grateful to God, well we're not
doing that anymore. We're exiled from the land, right? So בונה ירושלים
*Boneh Yerushalayim* looks back towards that time when we will have once
again be in that land. Of course that's pretty funny because if
you think that the third ברכה *bracha* is part of the ברכות
*brachos* or part of the, you know, the theme from the תורה
Torah *Torah*, how could a theme from the תורה *Torah* be בונה
ירושלים *Boneh Yerushalayim* which would indicate that it's currently destroyed? But anyway,
but then once we're talking about sort of self-sovereignty
in the land of Israel and restoring that, so a final ברכה
*bracha* that is about ביתר *Beitar*, which if you think about it
was actually about a like a, you know, about people that were
too like pushing for that a little bit too soon, before the
time, right, and they were trying to restore it like a little
bit too soon, דחקו את הקץ *dachaku es haketz*. So anyway there's
an interesting question like what are these last ברכות *brachos* doing there
in ברכת המזון *Birkas Hamazon*? But we are saying that, you know,
that they established this ברכה הטוב והמטיב *bracha hatov vehameitiv* and what's
הטוב והמטיב *Hatov Vehameitiv*? הטוב שלא הסריחו *Hatov shelo hisrichu*, God it
was good that He caused them not to stench, that the bodies
were still preserved when it was time to bury them, והמטיב *ve-hameitiv*,
and He does good, שניתנו לקבורה *shenisnu likvura*, that they were able
to be buried. Normally the והמטיב *vehameitiv* part means that not only
good to the immediate beneficiaries but that it's a good that other
people experience as well, so presumably it was not only good to
the, you know, to the corpses but like the עם *am* was
able to feel that they had now buried those bodies and dealt
with them properly.
Yeah, life affirming so it turns to courtship I guess.
What? I guess, I don't know how burial is life-affirming. I mean
it's nice that you were able to show
the presence, like the vitality maybe? Oh maybe. Or then confront this
depression, you know, you've...
right, like a sense that right, we were killed but we're repopulating.
Ah you mean the sense that we continue on even in the
face of tragedy. Okay, maybe. Yes, maybe that's also similar to the
idea of כלו מתי מדבר midbar? *kalu mesei midbar*. Right, they died
out and then the next generation now is going to start new
and go into the land. But still, the courtship theme is a
little more subtle according to these answers.
Yes, can I offer a non-rational explanation? Go for
it. I mean you put things in the ground in the hope
that they will grow.
Oh, you mean sort of like like procreation. תחיית המתים *techiyas hamaisim*,
exactly.
Yeah, like תחיית המתים *techiyas hamaisim* is connected to God bringing the
rain, right, and then it sprouts back up. Aha, so the association
of that with fertility and so on and birth. Right.
I don't know if that's... as you are rational...
No, not at all, it's just I mean I don't see explicitly
the theme of תחיית המתים *techiyas hamaisim* mentioned here, but you're right
that might be in the subtext or in the background.
And also some say this blessing when the
rains come, some say that.
Right, הטוב והמטיב *Hatov Vehameitiv* is a more general one. Oh, right,
that's a nice idea, yes.
And can I just interpose on the word הסריח *hisriach*? Yes. It
takes me to פרקי אבות *Pirkei Avos* where it says ולא הסריח
בשר הקודש מעולם *velo hisriach besar hakodesh me'olam*, like it's not
a word that's used too often. Aha. I was thinking about that
based on what Rabbi Do said. What? That it's another thing you
want to quote from פרקי אבות *Pirkei Avos*, טיפה סרוחה *tipa srucha*,
which refers to semen and for also that theme, but anyway, interesting.
Okay, בונה ירושלים *Boneh Yerushalayim*, that's... Oh, the connection that using that
word in the context of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. Okay, רב או רב יוסף
Yosef, *Rav o Rav Yosef*... רבא ורב יוסף Yosef דאמרי תרווייהו, so
yet another answer. יום שפוסקין בו מליכות עצים למערכה. Yom shepaskin bo
milichos etzim l'ma'arakha.
So over the summer they wanted good dry wood for the מערכה,
Ma'arakha, for the temple, for the top of the altar for the
temple, and they would cut it in the summer when it was
nice and dry because if it were to be have too much
moisture in it, it would create all of this like smoke, and
also presumably if it was dry it wouldn't have worms, if there
was moisture the worms would get into it. So they did this
cutting over the summer. ט"ו באב, Tu B'Av, right, is sort of
like the height of the summer. After ט"ו באב, Tu B'Av, the
days start to get shorter, right, so the days get shorter well
before that. Oh, they do? Okay. But the sun is maybe at
its height at ט"ו באב Tu B'Av or whatever. So really, when
did the days start to get shorter?
The peak is in June, right, then it starts going...
Right, the summer solstice is June 20th, yeah, that's true, that's true,
that's true. So the days get shorter, but the months get hotter,
the days get hotter still until that point. Okay, so so far.
So the days are getting less hot, so therefore they would stop
doing it at ט"ו באב Tu B'Av because then once the summer
started waning, they didn't want to continue cutting the wood, they were
afraid it would be wormy or would be too moist or whatever.
Now, why was that a day of joy?
Apparently the רשב"ם Rashbam says, well, they were doing this big מצוה
mitzvah the whole summer, chopping wood and whatever, and finally they completed
the מצוה, mitzvah, so it was a day of joy. What this
has to do with courtship, I don't have any idea. Okay,
so somebody can come up with something. Where was it?
What do you say connections between the harvest, like in pagan or
whatever cultures, like some harvest festivals, right, and like the Bacchanalia,
right, like courtship.
Right, so correct, but I don't see the chopping harvest, right, as
you think like the cutting of the wood and the heat of
the summer about harvest. Could be.
I mean, right,
I mean, yeah, some do say that the פסוק pasuk by particularly
by what do you call it, by by by נטע רבעי, Neta
Revai, when it says קודש הלולים לה' Kodesh Hillulim l'Hashem by the
fourth year, so I think someone wants to say that the הלולים
Hillulim is like from the word of like חלולים chalulim and refers
to like when they would do dances in circles during the harvest
period. So yes, I mean, obviously it seems that this is connected
to some, right, larger type of, you know, harvest-related
thing, this dancing and the courtship and so on. תנו רבנן רבי
אליעזר הגדול אומר כיון שהגיע חמשה עשר באב תשש כוחה של חמה.
Tanu Rabbanan Rabbi Eliezer ha-Gadol omer kivan she-higia chamisha asar b'Av tashash
kocha shel chamah. After the fifteenth of Av, the heat of the
sun is waning, and they would no longer be chopping the wood,
right?
תשש כוחה, tashash kocha, right.
Now, אמר רב מנשה וקרו ליה יום תבר מגל,
Amar Rav Menashe
v'karu lei yom tavar magal,
they called it the day of the breaking of the hatchet because
they would like put the hatchet away for the summer.
Bury the hatchet, oh good. מכאן ואילך, Mikan v'eilach, from this point
on, דמוסיף יוסיף, de-mosif yosif, the one who adds will be added
to him, שאינו מוסיף יאסף, she-eino mosif ye'asef, and the one who
doesn't add will come to an end. So מה יוסיף? ma yosif?
So what does it mean add? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says it
means if you add time to your learning of תורה. This is
why I got confused because the רשב"ם Rashbam says that after ט"ו
באב, Tu B'Av, the days start getting shorter. So since I heard
that everybody pointed out they got shorter earlier, but this is what
the רשב"ם Rashbam says, and since the days start getting shorter, you
have to, you should be adding on time in the nighttime to
your learning. You have so much daylight in the summer, you're spending
all this time learning, what else are you doing in the summer?
Okay, but once, once the night starts coming in earlier, you need
to start adding on time into the nighttime. That's the way he
reads it. So it doesn't exactly fit given the point that everybody
made, which is the days already start to get shorter a month
ago, but anyway, yes.
If ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shvat is ראש השנה לאילנות, Rosh Hashanah la-Ilanot,
ט"ו באב Tu B'Av
is six months after to
the second half of the year, whatever.
Right, it's a nice parallel to ט"ו בשבט, Tu B'Shvat, I hadn't
thought about that, yeah. So and if you don't use the opportunity
to be adding on time to your learning, maybe, then you'll come
to an end. מה יאסף? ma ye'asef? תנו רבי יוסף יאסף יוסף,
tanu Rabbi Yosef ye'asef yosef, right, תקבריה אימיה, tikberei imei,
that's lovely, his mother should bury him. Oy, so that's like a
very anti-climactic or discordant end to all this discussion of this joyous
period. Anyway, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught, שבעה כפלו את
כל העולם כולו, shiva kiflu es kol ha-olam kulo,
seven people if you buy seven lives get you from the beginning
of the world to the end of time. Now what this has
to do with anything we learned is not clear. The רשב"ם Rashbam
says maybe the idea is that these people lived so long because
they were learning תורה. That's what he said, like if you learn
תורה, days will be added to your
life to
דמוסיף יוסיף, de-mosif yosif, so maybe that's the connection, I don't know,
it's not clear what the connection is.
Somehow folded the whole world, like the entire history of time is
folded into their lives.
לקפל L'kappel is to fold.
Yeah, it is, right?
Yeah. Yeah.
So somehow like the entire world is folded into of the history
of the world is folded into their lives. Who were they? מתושלח
ראה אדם. Metushelach ra'ah Adam. So if you go ahead and you
read בראשית, Bereishit, you'll see that מתושלח Metushelach and אדם Adam overlap.
So from אדם Adam to מתושלח. Metushelach. שם ראה מתושלח. Shem ra'ah
Metushelach. שם Shem and מתושלח Metushelach overlap. יעקב ראה את שם. Yaakov
ra'ah et Shem. יעקב Yaakov and שם Shem overlap. The days, the
days, I mean, again, this is like if you do the math
in the תורה you'll see that this is correct. Okay, now עמרם
ראה את יעקב. Amram ra'ah et Yaakov. Now that is not explicit,
but the רשבם Rashbam says it's מסברא mis'vara because it says יעקב
Yaakov came down to מצרים Mitzrayim with קהת. Kehat. עמרם Amram was
קהת Kehat's son, oldest son, and
and from the time יעקב Yaakov came down to מצרים Mitzrayim till
he died was seventeen years. So the רשבם Rashbam says well, it
makes sense, if קהת Kehat was alive and by the time יעקב
Yaakov died he was already at least seventeen, eighteen years old, he
probably had already had his first son by that time. Okay? So
that's not explicit, but we're making that assertion that עמרם Amram overlapped
with יעקב. Yaakov. אחיה השילוני ראה את עמרם. Achiyah HaShiloni ra'ah et
Amram. Now that's a little strange, right? אחיה השילוני Achiyah HaShiloni was
a prophet in the time of way later, right? When's אחיה השילוני?
Achiyah HaShiloni? In the days of
ירבעם בן נבט. Yarovam ben Nevat. Right,
thank
you, the days of ירבעם בן נבט. Yarovam ben Nevat. So that
was a few years later, okay? So how we're assuming that he
overlapped with עמרם Amram is not at all clear, especially since עמרם
Amram died in מצרים, Mitzrayim, right? Because if you think about it,
right, if עמרם Amram was 137 years old and we're assuming that
he was born right at the beginning of the time they were
in מצרים, Mitzrayim, which is what we sort of just said, and
they left מצרים Mitzrayim right after like 210 years or whatever, so
עמרם Amram basically had like died out way from the time that
they had been in מצרים. Mitzrayim. So אחיה השילוני Achiyah HaShiloni had
to be alive in מצרים Mitzrayim to see עמרם, Amram, come out
from מצרים, Mitzrayim, enter in to the land of ישראל, okay, and
live for about, I don't know, a thousand years, okay, or five,
I didn't do the exact math, seven hundred years. So A, we
have him living for hundreds and hundreds of years, and B, like
what ever happened about the point that anybody who came out of
מצרים Mitzrayim died in the מדבר? midbar.
He'd be a kid in the מדבר. midbar?
אחיה, Achiyah, a kid died in the desert?
Well, עמרם Amram died at 137, so anybody who saw עמרם Amram
was about 70 years old when they left מצרים, Mitzrayim, because if
they assumed they were in מצרים Mitzrayim for 210 years.
So he wouldn't have died in the desert then because he was
over...
well we're going to give that answer. Okay, but we don't know
that yet. Right, עמרם, Amram, okay, עמרם Amram died at 137 and
we're assuming he was born during the beginning of their period in
מצרים. Mitzrayim. So anybody who saw עמרם Amram alive was at least
70 when they left. And now we have to assume that he
lived through the period of the desert, went into ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael and lived for 500 or whatever years afterwards.
So he can't be 70 years before the Exodus because then he
can't have משה.
Moshe Right, well משה was 80. I don't understand, what what are
you saying? Right. Okay.
So אחיה השילוני Achiyah HaShiloni was very old.
Yeah.
But also first of all we gotta assert that he was about
a few hundred years old. Number two though, how did he get
into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael if he was supposed to die in
the desert? So let's take a look.
Okay. אליהו ראה את אחיה השילוני. Eliyahu ra'ah et Achiyah HaShiloni. אליהו
Eliyahu saw אחיה השילוני, Achiyah HaShiloni,
which actually is in the פסוקים pesukim I believe. ועדיין קיים, ve'adayin
kayam, and אליהו Eliyahu we know is still alive. So once you
get to אליהו, Eliyahu, you get the rest of the history of
the world right there. Okay, ואחיה השילוני ראה את עמרם? v'Achiyah HaShiloni
ra'ah et Amram? Did אחיה השילוני Achiyah HaShiloni see עמרם? Amram? והכתיב
לא נותר מהם איש כי אם כלב בן יפונה ויהושע בן נון.
Vehak'tiv lo notar mehem ish ki im Kalev ben Yefuneh v'Yehoshua bin
Nun. So
it doesn't even say first of all why are we assuming אחיה
השילוני Achiyah HaShiloni was the link? I don't know. But once we're
assuming that, how do you even... and we're going to be willing
to assume that he lived hundreds and hundreds of years, but how
could he have survived the period of the desert? So אמר רב
המנונא לא נגזרה גזירה על שבטו של לוי. Amar Rav Hamnuna lo
nigzera gezeira al shivto shel Levi. אחיה השילוני Achiyah HaShiloni was a
לוי Levi and לוי Levi wasn't included in the גזירה. gezeira. דכתיב
במדבר הזה יפלו פגריכם וכל
פקודיכם לכל מספרכם מבן עשרים שנה ומעלה. Dich'tiv bamidbar hazeh yiflu pigreichim
v'chol p'kudeichem l'chol misparchem miben esrim shanah vamalah. All of your corpses
will fall, all of your counting to all your
numbers, from twenty years up. מי שפקודיו מבן עשרים, mi shep'kudav miben
esrim, those that are counted from twenty. יצא שבטו של לוי שפקודיו
מבן שלושים. yatza shivto shel Levi shep'kudav miben shloshim. לוי Levi is
counted from the age of thirty, thirty to fifty, right? It says
יבוא לצבא צבא בעבודת אהל מועד. yavo litzbo tzava ba'avodat Ohel Moed.
And the רשבם Rashbam points out the similarity of the language, right,
when it counts בני ישראל from twenty, it says כל הבא לצבא.
kol haba latzava. So there's the army of, you know, there's the
army of like fighting in the battle. And then there's like צבאות
השם, Tzivot Hashem, right, and then there's the ליובאוויטש Lubavitch צבאות השם,
Tzivot Hashem, exactly, the army of God, okay, and anyway, it's the
same term, so in this term, even though it's this borrowed concept
of being in the army for the לוי, Levi, it's thirty years
old, so they weren't part of the same counting. So therefore, the
גזירה gezeira did not apply to them. So although the פסוקים psukim
say that the only people who survived were יהושע Yehoshua and כלב,
Kalev, what we're really saying is the entire tribe of לוי Levi
could have survived. Now some people would have died
naturally, okay, but there were many people in לוי Levi that maybe
kept, you know, went into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. that were from
that generation. Okay.
Wait, what's the decree against? What's the age for being in the
army? Twenty to sixty? Right.
So if you're over- we're getting there, you're already anticipating. You're playing
Michael's role now. You're anticipating the גמרא. Gemara, We're not there yet.
Okay.
Yes. Before the advent of this דרשה, drasha, should we
actually- should- is it פשט pshat in the תורה itself that לוי,
Levi, that שבט לוי Shevet Levi didn't die in the מדבר?
Yeah, I don't know, I mean, the- right, right.
In other words, they didn't part-
Yeah, I mean, it says וכל מספרכם לכל פקודיכם, v'chol misparchem l'chol
pkudeichem, so it could- yeah, I mean, it is true, there was
a different- לוי Levi was always seen as separate. Yeah. So the
גמרא Gemara says ומשאר שבטים לא הוו? u'mishar shvatim lo ayu? One
minute, you mean to tell me that after we got through saying
that the פסוק pasuk, says that only יהושע Yehoshua and כלב, Kalev,
and now we're saying, oh, except for the whole tribe of לוי.
Levi. And now we're saying wait, wait, wait, other tribes also got
in, in, you know, despite the פסוקים. psukim. והתניא, v'ha tanya, יאיר
בן מנשה, Ya'ir ben Menashe, מכיר בן מנשה, Machir ben Menashe, נולדו
בימי יעקב. noldu bi'mei Yaakov. So יאיר בן מנשה Ya'ir ben Menashe
and מכיר בן מנשה Machir ben Menashe were born in the times
of יעקב. Yaakov. We don't- it's not explicit about this, but whatever.
Wait, what does it say? It says by יוסף, it says, what
does it say? Who says ילדו- yoldu נולדו על ברכי יוסף. noldu
al birkei Yosef. What does it say? גם בני מכיר בן מנשה,
gam bnei Machir ben Menashe, right? It says that? Does it say
גם בני מכיר בן מנשה gam bnei Machir ben Menashe נולדו על
ברכי
יוסף?
noldu al
birkei Yosef?
פינחס בן יאיר... Pinchas ben Yair... anyway.
I think it says that at the end of בראשית, Bereishit, right?
What does it say? Michael was here, he'd know right away. Okay.
Try the end. Yeah,
וירא יוסף לאפרים בני שלשים
גם בני
מכיר בן מנשה ילדו על ברכי יוסף.
v'ayar Yosef l'Ephraim bnei shileshim
gam bnei Machir ben
Menashe
yuldu
al birkei Yosef.
So the sons of מכיר Machir were born when יוסף was alive,
so we're assuming that מכיר Machir himself was born when יעקב Yaakov
was alive. Okay, so anyway, so יאיר בן מנשה, Ya'ir ben Menashe,
מכיר בן מנשה Machir ben Menashe נולדו בימי יעקב, noldu bi'mei Yaakov,
ולא מתו עד שנכנסו ישראל לארץ. v'lo meisu ad shenichnesu Yisrael la'aretz.
And they lived till the entry into the land. How do you
know? שנאמר: shene'emar: ויכו מהם אנשי העי כשלושים וששה איש. vayaku mehem
anshei ha'Ai k'shloshim v'shisha ish. Okay, in the battle of העי, Ha'Ai,
like thirty-six people were killed. ותניא, v'tanya, we learned in a ברייתא:
braita. שלושים וששה ממש, shloshim v'shisha mamash, literally thirty-six, דברי רבי יהודה.
divrei Rabbi Yehuda. אמר לו רבי נחמיה: amar lo Rabbi Nechemia: וכי
נאמר שלושים וששה? v'chi ne'emar shloshim v'shisha? It doesn't say thirty-six. הלא
נאמר, halo ne'emar, לא נאמר אלא כשלושים וששה, lo ne'emar ela k'shloshim
v'shisha, like thirty-six. אלא זה יאיר בן מנשה ששקול כרובה של סנהדרין.
ela zeh Ya'ir ben Menashe sheshakul k'rubah shel Sanhedrin. This is יאיר
בן מנשה, Ya'ir ben Menashe,
which is as weighty as the רובה של סנהדרין. rubah shel Sanhedrin.
סנהדרין Sanhedrin is seventy-one, so thirty-six is the majority of a סנהדרין.
Sanhedrin. Why we're identifying יאיר בן מנשה Ya'ir ben Menashe with רובה
של סנהדרין, rubah shel Sanhedrin, I don't know, but whatever it is,
he's claiming that יאיר בן מנשה Ya'ir ben Menashe made it into
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So he lived from the time of יעקב,
Yaakov, like we're saying of אחיה השילוני, Achiyah Hashiloni, all the way
through the desert into getting into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. What happened
about everybody who was supposed to die out in the desert?
What happened to צלפחד who passed away? He should be one of
the exceptions.
Oh, that's an interesting point. Right.
צלפחד centered around the tribe of מנשה. Menashe.
Oh yeah, that's a good point too. How does he say- you're
into all the earlier discussions about who inherited from מנשה. Menashe. Yeah,
that's a good question.
I'd have to think about that. Okay, so it says, אלא אמר
רב אחא בר יעקב: ela amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov: לא נגזרה
גזירה לא על פחות מבן עשרים ולא על יתר מבן שישים, lo
nigzra gezeira lo al pachos miben esrim v'lo al yeser miben shishim,
like David was saying. Ah, so besides that לוי Levi was off,
if you were over sixty years old, now it also didn't apply
to you. Maybe you died a natural death. I mean, it did
take forty years, so anybody who was over sixty who made it
in would have had to have been a hundred. But anyway, but
the גזירה gezeira wasn't made. So there could have been people that
were over sixty that made it into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. לא
פחות מבן עשרים דכתיב מבן עשרים שנה ומעלה, lo pachos miben esrim
d'chtiv miben esrim shana v'ma'ala, ולא על יתר מבן שישים, v'lo al
yeser miben shishim, גמר מעלה מעלה מערכין. gamar ma'ala ma'ala m'erchin.
Okay, by ערכין Erchin it says for somebody who is sixty years
and above. So מה להלן יתר מבן שישים כפחות מבן כ"ף. ma
lahalan yeter miben shishim kepachot miben chaf. The same way by ערכין
erchin if you're over sixty years old, you're like less than twenty.
Now the רשב"ם Rashbam says it is not true that the amount
is the same for over sixty and under twenty, but it means
you're not treated in the twenty to sixty category. Okay, you're different
than the twenty to sixty category. So there's a difference between under
twenty and over sixty. אף כאן יתר מבן שישים כפחות מבן עשרים.
af kan yeter miben shishim kepachot miben esrim.
So now we have, as sort of David anticipated, I think because
רש"י Rashi says in the חומש Chumash or whatever, like, you know,
people like this idea that after saying that the only people who
survived were כלב Kalev and יהושע, Yehoshua, first of all we have
the רשב"ם Rashbam earlier who said that fifteen thousand got their decree
waived. Now we have saying it didn't apply to all of לוי
Levi and it didn't apply to anybody over the age of sixty.
So we're able to say that יאיר בן מנשה Yair ben Menashe
made it into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael And we're able to say
that אחיה השילוני, Achiyah HaShiloni, right, who saw עמרם, Amram, you know,
and left מצרים Mitzrayim when he was at the age of seventy,
made it all the way through the desert, he was over sixty,
came into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. and lived for hundreds of years
afterwards until he saw אליהו. Eliyahu. Why we're making that assertion by
אחיה השילוני Achiyah HaShiloni I have no idea. Yes.
I missed something about about יאיר בן מנשה Yair ben Menashe being
שקול כרוב של סנהדרין. shakul kerov shel Sanhedrin. Was thirty-six? Is not
a number of a סנהדרין. Sanhedrin.
It's the majority of the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin.
About a רובא. ruba. Right.
Thirty-six times two is seventy-two. סנהדרין Sanhedrin is seventy-one. If you need
to get a majority of votes in the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, you need
thirty-six.
That's right. That's right.
Okay. So let's continue the next thing. Okay, so now the גמרא,
Gemara, so that was sort of like a mostly that דף there
was like working out this idea of ט"ו באב Tu B'Av and
this אגדתא agadata and now we get back to some more discussions.
I mean it's still going to be a lot of פסוקים, pesukim,
but we get back to some more discussions about the division of
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael So let's just begin this. איבעיא להו, ibaia
lehu, they raised the question, ארץ ישראל לשבטים איפלוג או דילמא לקרקף
גברי איפלוג. Eretz Yisrael leshvatim iplog o dilma lekarkaf gavrei iplog. How
was it divided? Was it divided into twelve equal sections and then
if you were a numerous tribe, each person got a small portion
and if you were a small tribe, each person got a large
portion? Or was it divided according to the number of people? So
the size of a tribe section would have been proportional to the
number of people. So the obvious answer is B, not just because
it's more fair, but if you read the פסוקים pesukim in יהושע,
Yehoshua, right, and you see this lovely map here that we have
from מיכל, Michal, right, the amounts of the tribes are clearly different
sizes, right? So it was not twelve equal sections. Okay, it really
does seem proportional to the size of the tribe. But nevertheless, the
גמרא's Gemara conclusion is going to be that they were twelve equal
portions and every individual, if you were part of a numerous tribe,
you got a smaller portion per person, if you're part of a
small tribe, you got a much larger portion per person. So תא
שמע, ta shema, come and hear, we'll just start this on the
next דף.
בין רב למעט, bein rav lemaat, it says to these you should
divide the land whether a lot or a little, right? It's a
very strange פסוק, pasuk right? One
פסוק says לרב תרבה נחלתו ולמעט תמעיט נחלתו, larav tarbeh nachalato velamaat
tamit nachalato, to the many give many and to the few give
a few. And then it says this is how you should divide
the land, בין רב למעט, bein rav lemaat, whether many or few.
So how do you what are those פסוקים pesukim saying? So it
says that this בין רב למעט bein rav lemaat means that each
tribe gets the same section of land, the same amount of land,
whether they are a numerous tribe or not a numerous tribe. Within
a tribe, each individual gets the same amount, okay, or whatever, or
you know, but or something like that. But anyway, but every tribe
gets the same amount of land, בין רב למעט. bein rav lemaat.
ותניא, vetanya, עתידה ארץ ישראל שתתחלק לשלושה עשר שבטים. atidah Eretz Yisrael
shetitchalek lishloshah asar shevatim. At that time, it was divided into twelve
segments, but in the future, ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. will be divided
into thirteen segments. So בתחילה לא נתחלקה אלא לשנים עשר שבטים batchilah
lo nitchalkah ela lishneim asar shevatim
to twelve. ולא נתחלקה אלא בכסף, velo nitchalkah ela bekesef, and it
was only done based on, somebody asked this question before, is it
everybody got the same area or everybody got the same value of
land? Right? So, you know, are you getting something in the middle
of New York City, are you getting in the middle of ירושלים
or תל אביב Tel Aviv or are you getting something in some
barren area, you know, outside of any city? Right? So it's not
it's not all about the amount of area. So this claims, seems
to say, we'll see it in the גמרא, Gemara that everybody's amount
of land was of equal value even if the size of land
was not the same. Now, you could do that in one of
two ways. You could give people different sizes, so you get three
acres, you know, in the middle of some wheat field and I
get a quarter of an inch in the middle of Central Park,
you know?
So you could give people different sizes or you could give everybody
the same size and then you have to pay the difference, right?
So everybody gets the same size and then you figure out what
the different value is and somehow, you know, you redistribute money in
order to make up the difference. But anyway, but it was divided
based on value, not based on size, שנאמר, shenemar, בין רב למעט.
bein rav lemaat.
Not exactly clear how that means that it was equal value. Anyway,
אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav Yehudah, סאה ביהודה שווה חמש סאין בגליל,
seah biYehudah shaveh chamesh sein baGalil, right, one סאה, seah, one. An
acre in Judah let's say is worth five acres in the Galilee.
Really true? Really true.
A million מעלות maalos but you could get like one fifty. Okay.
ולא נחלקה אלא
בגורל
V’lo nechalka ella
b’goral
and it was divided by a lot שנאמר אך בגורל תחלק הארץ.
shenemar ach begoral techalek ha’aretz. ולא נחלקה אלא באורים ותומים V’lo nechalka
ella b’Urim v’Tummim
and it was done with the assistance of the אורים ותומים Urim
v’Tummim שנאמר על פי הגורל shenemar al pi hagoral by the mouth
of the גורל. goral. So there was some oracle, there was some
speech, so there was something that emerged from the אורים ותומים Urim
v’Tummim that the כהן heard who was getting what. So הא כיצד
Ha keitzad and how was it both by lots and by the
oracle of the אורים ותומים? Urim v’Tummim? So אלעזר מלובש אורים ותומים,
Elazar melubash Urim v’Tummim, Elazar was dressed with the אורים ותומים Urim
v’Tummim ויהושע וכל ישראל עומדים לפניו v’Yehoshua v’chol Yisrael omdim lefanav and
Yehoshua and all of the Israel people were gathered there.
וקלפי, V’kalfi, thank you, של שבטים וקלפי של תחומים מונחים לפניו shel
shevatim v’kalfi shel tchumim munachim lefanav and he had one box filled
with on it filled with
like placards or whatever they are, you know, that had on it
the names of the tribes and one box filled with you know
pieces of wood or whatever they would be that had on it
the names of the different sections of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
וקלפי של תחומים מונח לפניו V’kalfi shel tchumim munach lefanav והיו מכוונים
ברוח הקודש ואומר v’hayu mechavnim b’Ruach HaKodesh v’omer and before he did
the drawing then the אורים ותומים Urim v’Tummim sort of through the
אורים ותומים Urim v’Tummim he prophesied how the drawing would turn out.
And he would say זבולון עולה תחום עכו, Zevulun oleh tchum Akko,
Zevulun is going to get the boundary that boundaries on Akko. Although
as they say Akko itself actually wasn't from זבולון, Zevulun, it was
in אשר but okay, but up to the boundary of Akko.
ותחום עכו עולה עמו V’tchum Akko oleh imo I'm about to pick
זבולון Zevulun from this box and I will pick the Akko section
from this box. טרף בקלפי Taraf b’kalfi he mixed up the lot
של שבטים shel shevatim ועלה בידו זבולון v’alah beyado Zevulun and he
picked one and lo and behold it was Zevulun. טרף בקלפי של
תחומים Taraf b’kalfi shel tchumim he mixed up the lots in the
box that had the lots of the boundaries ועלה בידו תחום עכו
v’alah beyado tchum Akko and then it came up. Now רשב"ם Rashbam
says the reason is so people should realize it's from God and
it wasn't by chance. Right, if you just draw and you draw
whatever, it's like whoa, that was like bad luck, we got this
lousy section, we wanted a different section. But if it's assisted by
this prophecy, then you know that it's all from God. Of course,
one could also imagine that because by this prophecy you might think
the whole thing is rigged. Right, you're telling me ahead of time
what you're about to draw. I mean I guess when he drew
it people saw what was in his hand, but it's still like
you know sorting hat from Harry Potter.
Oh, there you go.
Anyway, okay. And okay.
Now where were we?
Don't we have already בברכת יעקב, b’virkat Yaakov, זבולון לחוף ימים ישכון?
Zevulun le’chof yamim yishkon?
Yeah, but it doesn't say which, there's a lot of חוף ימים
chof yamim here.
Right? I mean, could be any. Right?
Okay.
Now then he said נפתלי, Naftali, now he said וחוזר ומכוין ברוח
הקודש ואומר, v’chozer u’mechavein b’Ruach HaKodesh v’omer, נפתלי עולה דתחום גינוסר עולה
עמו Naftali oleh d’tchum Ginosar oleh imo
I'm going to get נפתלי Naftali and I'll get the גינוסר Ginosar
section. Right, גינוסר, Ginosar, right,
the כנרת. Kinneret. טרף בקלפי של שבטים ועלה בידו נפתלי, Taraf b’kalfi
shel shevatim v’alah beyado Naftali, טרף בקלפי של תחומים ועלה בידו תחום
גינוסר taraf b’kalfi shel tchumim v’alah beyado tchum Ginosar וכן כל שבט
ושבט. v’chein kol shevet v’shevet.
And that worked out and that's how they divided it. So that's
what was the way it was in the time of יהושע, Yehoshua,
but that's not going to be the way it's going to be
לעתיד לבוא. le’asid lavo. ולא כחלוקה של עולם הזה חלוקה של עולם
הבא. V’lo k’chaluka shel Olam HaZeh chaluka shel Olam HaBa.
Now
this is very interesting. עולם הבא Olam HaBa you normally think it
means you go to heaven and you're up in the sky there
with God or whatever it is. Okay, first of all, עולם הבא
Olam HaBa in חז"ל often means, I'm serious, that's what people think
when you say the word עולם הבא. Olam HaBa. Okay, but עולם
הבא Olam HaBa in the גמרא Gemara usually refers, that was had
a heavy influence from רמב"ם, Rambam, that we think עולם הבא Olam
HaBa means the world I will be in after I pass from
this world. But עולם הבא Olam HaBa in the גמרא Gemara much
more means the future world that will be in the times of
משיח Mashiach that we're all be living in in this physical planet,
not up in some spiritual existence, that we're all going to be
living on this planet at the time of משיח. Mashiach. Okay, so
that world so that division in those future messianic times is not
going to be like the division at the time of ארץ ישראל.
העולם הזה HaOlam HaZeh אדם יש לו שדה לבן אין לו שדה
פרדס, adam yesh lo sadeh lavan ein lo sadeh pardes, שדה פרדס
אין לו שדה לבן. sadeh pardes ein lo sadeh lavan. This world
some people got a wheat field, they didn't get an orchard, you
got an orchard you didn't get a wheat field. בעולם הבא אין
לך כל אחד ואחד שאין לו בהר ובשפילה ובעמק, B’Olam HaBa ein
lecha kol echad v’echad she’ein lo bahar u’vashefeilah u’va’emek,
everybody's portion will get a little bit of everything: mountain and valley
and the flatlands. שנאמר שער ראובן אחד שער יהודה אחד שער לוי
אחד, Shenemar shaar Reuven echad shaar Yehuda echad shaar Levi echad,
so everybody will get like an equal section. והקדוש ברוך הוא מחלק
להן בעצמו V’HaKadosh Baruch Hu m’chalek lahen b’atzmo and you're not going
to have אלעזר Elazar doing it, God'll do the distributing. distribution, שנאמר
shenemar ואלה מחלקותם ve-eleh machlekotam נאום השם, neum Hashem, and
this is the division, says God. So that's the end of that
ברייתא. braita, Okay, in the future it'll be thirteen sections, not twelve.
Everybody's going to get a little of everything. God is going to
divide it, fine. Anyway, why is this relevant for us? קתני מיהא,
katani mi-ha, we teach nevertheless, שבתחילה לא נתחלקה אלא לשנים עשר שבטים.
she-be-tchilla lo nitchalka ella li-shneim asar shevatim.
It was divided into twelve. So presumably that means twelve equal sections.
שמע מינה shema mina לשבטים איפלוג, li-shvatim i-palug, you see it was
divided into the שבטים, shevatim, שמע מינה, shema mina, that's a good
proof. I got to tell you, I don't understand it. How do
you know just because it was twelve sections, it means that they
were all of equal size? Maybe they were of different sizes. So,
but some for whatever reason, the גמרא's Gemara. assuming that because of
בין רב למעט bein rav le-me-at and of this ברייתא, it tells
us that they were twelve equal sizes. And therefore, individuals got, if
you were, you didn't want to be part of a numerous tribe,
because you were part of a numerous tribe, according to the way
this imagines it, you actually got a much smaller piece. Okay, in
the actual division as we've seen, the sections really were proportional or
of varying sizes, but this גמרא certainly seems to conclude that they
were of the same size. All right, we will continue with this
גמרא. So imagine
if you...